Okay boker tov, today's דף daf is י"ב, yud bet, עבודה זרה
Avoda Zara 12, and we pick up at the גמרא Gemara after
the משנה Mishna at the very bottom of י"א עמוד ב'. yud
aleph amud bet. We spent a good amount of time yesterday discussing
the משנה, Mishna, but let's just read it again just to quickly
just to reorient ourselves. עיר שיש בה עבודת כוכבים, Ir sheyesh ba
avodat kochavim, if you have a city that has in it an
עבודה זרה avoda zara which we will take to mean either that
it is a יום איד yom eid for the עבודה זרה avoda
zara keeping in the context for the first משנה, Mishna, or possibly
a special market day specifically devoted to that עבודה זרה. avoda zara.
So
חוצה לה מותר, chutz lah mutar, outside of the city you are
permitted to do
business whether not restricted by the יום איד yom eid issues and
not a concern in terms of the markets. היה
חוצה לה עבודת כוכבים, Haya chutz lah avodat kochavim, if this יום
איד yom eid or the market day was taking place outside of
the city and let's say one of the villages outside of the
city, then תוכה מותר, tocha mutar, then inside it's
permissible. So each you assume that it's based on the region, you
don't say one place is dragged after the next. מהו לילך לשם,
Mahu leilech lesham, are you allowed to go to the city for
your own business if they're celebrating, they're in the middle of their
celebrations and it's going to look like you're going to participate or
that actually as we discussed yesterday the actual going itself like a
pilgrimage might be seen as a form of participation? So בזמן שהדרך
מיוחדת לאותו מקום אסור, bizman shehaderech meyuchadeset leoto makom assur,
if there is the path, the street only goes to that city
and does not leave outside of the city, then it's forbidden, then
people will think that you're going to participate
or that your going is itself a form of participation, they'll think
that it's all connected to the holiday or to the market day.
ואם היה יכול להלך במקום אחר מותר, veim haya yachol lehalach bemakom
acher mutar, but if it was possible, if the street was a
highway that cut through the city and then continued on to another
city, then even if your terminal point is the city itself, people
who see you going there don't assume that you're going to the
city, they'll think that you're passing through and you're going beyond. So
therefore there's no concern about appearances because there's an easy alternative interpretation.
However if they think that your terminal point is the city then
there is a serious concern about how they might interpret that. Okay,
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. היכי דמי חוצה לה,
Heichi dami chutz lah, what would constitute outside of it like how
close to
outside would still be considered distinct even if it's really if it's
totally immediately outside the city is that still considered that it follows
a different rule? אמר ריש לקיש משום רבי חנינא, Amar Reish Lakish
mishum Rabbi Chanina, כגון אטלוזא של עזה, kegon atlusa shel Aza,
like the אטלוזא atlusa which is either the name of a town
outside of the city of Gaza or it means
a marketplace or where they sell meat or something. So when even
a place that's right outside of the city like this אטלוזא atlusa
outside of עזה, Aza, it is distinct that if the marketplace or
the יום איד yom eid is taking place in the city it
doesn't apply to this אטלוזא atlusa and vice versa. ואיכא דאמרי, Ve'ika
d'amri, others say, דבעי מיניה ריש לקיש מרבי חנינא, debaei minei Reish
Lakish meiRabbi Chanina,
that actually this was not an answer that Reish Lakish gave in
the name of Rabbi Chanina but it was a question that Reish
Lakish asked of Rabbi Chanina. אטלוזא של עזה מהו, Atlusa shel Aza
mahu, what's the status of אטלוזא של עזה, atlusa shel Aza, does
it follow עזה Aza or not follow עזה? Aza? אמר ליה, Amar
lei, and he said to him, לא הלכת לצור מימיך, lo halachta
leTzor miyamecha, have you never gone to the city of Tyre? Interesting,
pointing a different city. וראית ישראל ועובד כוכבים, Veraita Yisrael veovad kochavim,
and
seen a Jew and a non-Jew, top of י"ב עמוד א', yud
bet amud aleph, ששפתו שתי קדירות גבי כירה
אחת, sheshaftu shtei kideirot gabbei kira achat, that they were cooking two
pots on one כירה. kira. א כירה A kira was an oven
that basically had a fire on the inside of it and it
was sort of like a hollowed out
rectangular solid and on the top of it there were two circles
where you would lower the pots into and
so
if he said look it's very common practice in this city of
Tyre, apparently a lot of Jews and non-Jews, they would share an
oven, so imagine like you have two people, a Jew and a
non-Jew sharing an oven, one on one burner, one on the other
burner with two pots right next to each other. ולא חשו להם
חכמים, Velo chashu lahem chachamim, and the חכמים chachamim weren't concerned that
what was going on in the pot of the non-Jew would affect
the pot of the Jew. So this just seems like a colorful
analogy and basically saying it's possible two things are very close to
one another. other, and nevertheless they're distinct and here too just because
עזה Azah and אתלוזה Atlozah are very close, what goes on in
one does not affect the other. All right. So we could have
just ended there and just thought that he was using a colorful
analogy, but the גמרא Gemara takes this seriously, this analogy. And let's
see where the גמרא Gemara goes with this. מאי לא חשו להם
חכמים? Mai lo chashu lahem chachamim? What is it that the sages
were not concerned about? What could they have been concerned about in
a case of a Jew and a non-Jew cooking a pot, one
kosher one tref right next to each other? What was the thing
that they would have been a basis for concern, and they said
it's not a concern and then by analogy what should we learn
out in our case of this אתלוזה Atlozah and עזה Azah that
might be a concern but that we should learn from this analogy
that it's not a concern? So we're going to have three opinions
about this. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, says Abaye, משום בשר נבלה, mishum
basar neveilah, because it's a concern of non-kosher meat. לא אמינא דלמא
מהדר אפי ישראל לאחורי ושדי איהו כותי דנבלה בקדירה, Lo amina dilma
mahadar apei Yisrael leachorei v'shadi ihu koti d'neveilah b'kideira, that we're not
concerned that a non-Jew, the Jew would look away for a minute
and the non-Jew would just toss a piece of meat into, you
know, the pot of the Jew.
So we're not concerned for real concerns of טרפות. treifos. Now, there
are reasons why we may not be concerned. Number one is that
the non-Jew has no motivation to do it, you know, there's no
incentive. Why would he do that? I mean just to make the
Jew eat טרפות? treifos? So the, you know, there's a possible different
explanation. It's not that he would just סתם stam do it, but
that he might, you know, he might try to help the Jew
and take from his spoon and stir the Jew's pot and, you
know, and his spoon had טריפה treifa on it, טריפה treifa juices
or תוספות Tosafos says maybe, you know, the Jew had a nice
juicy piece of meat and he had a lean piece of meat
so he swapped it because of a financial benefit. So anyway, one
is like you have to make it a scenario where there's some
real basis to be concerned about. What would have motivated him to
do it? But even if there were some motivation, we're not concerned.
Okay, לא אמינא דלמא מהדר ישראל אפי לאחורי ושדי איהו כותי דנבלה
בקדירה. lo amina dilma mahadar Yisrael apei leachorei v'shadi ihu koti d'neveilah
b'kideira. Okay,
now one of the reasons of course that we're not concerned is,
you know, it goes to the whole question of what constitutes like
a השגחה hashgacha and a principle of יוצא ונכנס. yotzei v'nichnas. If
you have somebody doing spot inspections and here of course if the
Jew is right there, even if he's turned his head, he could
easily turn it back. And the fear that he might turn his
face back, you know, would be a reason that the non-Jew wouldn't
do it. Okay, so there's, okay, so whatever the reason is there
could have been a basis to be concerned about a דאורייתא d'oraisa
concern about נבלה neveilah and we're not concerned. Okay,
now,
so let's see the comparison. הכא נמי, Hacha nami, says Abaye, לא
חשו להם חכמים משום דמי עבודת כוכבים. lo chashu lahem chachamim mishum
d'mei avodas kochavim.
Here
too the analogy is to say we're not concerned that if you're
buying something in this marketplace of עזה, Azah, even though there's a
festival going on in עזה, Azah, that the non-Jew is going to
give you money that was, you know, proceeds of the sale of
an idol, real איסור דאורייתא. issur d'oraisa. Because if we're making an
analogy to a case that we're not concerned by an איסור דאורייתא
issur d'oraisa by the pots and the meat, so also there might
have been a basis to be concerned by an איסור דאורייתא issur
d'oraisa here. What איסור דאורייתא? issur d'oraisa? Doing business before the holiday
is not an איסור דאורייתא. issur d'oraisa.
So the איסור דאורייתא issur d'oraisa is something really טרפה treifa like
the טרפה treifa meat would be. You're concerned that maybe you're getting
money from the non-Jew that was proceeds of an idol and the
חידוש chiddush is that we're not concerned about that.
Now, to say one or two things about this. First of all,
there's a whole long תוספות Tosafos has a discussion. Is it really
true that proceeds of a sale of an idol that a non-Jew
sold are forbidden in benefit?
You know, there's whole discussions in the גמרא Gemara that if a
non-Jew is selling an idol maybe he does ביטול bittul on his
idol. So why should we be concerned that the even if this
money actually was, you know, proceeds of a sale, does it really
become forbidden? You know, other scenarios in which it might be forbidden.
Maybe it was a type of an offering that was, you know,
put before like a קרבן, korban, you know, that they actually give
an offering of money and maybe that's what makes it forbidden. What
exactly תוספות Tosafos has a discussion is the scenario in which the
money of that a non-Jew, you know, money he has relating to
an idol would actually be forbidden בהנאה דאורייתא. b'hana'ah d'oraisa. Okay, but
and the two basic explanations are either proceeds from a sale of
an idol, although there are questions about that, or money that was
given as an offering although there too what exactly, you know, what
are the parameters that it was given as an offering that would
make it אסור. assur. That's one issue. The second question is that
תוספות Tosafos says you know in all the discussions of this גמרא
Gemara about יום איד, yom eid, we're never concerned that the non-Jew
might even in the יום איד yom eid itself might have on
him money that is proceeds from the sale of an idol. So
here it's sounding like we're being lenient because it's in the market,
it's in אתלוזה Atlozah and not in עזה Azah itself. But תוספות...
Tosafos... Since when are we ever concerned about money of an idol
happens to be in the hands of a non-Jew? And it's because
of that that תוספות Tosafot says that we're dealing specifically not just
with a general יום איד, Yom Eid, but a specific market day
for this god. And since it's a specific market day, let's say
in עזה Azah for this god, then you know you could there's
a heightened concern that the people have money that actually is money
directly connected to the idol itself. Okay, so you have to understand
like why was this even a concern if in the rest of
the מסכת Masechet it's never concerned? So תוספות Tosafot because says it's
a special market day
and therefore it would be a concern
in
עזה Azah itself that somebody might be handling that money, but right
outside of it it's not a concern. And that's the analogy to
the בשר נבילה. basar neveilah. Even though you're dealing with something טריף
דאורייתא, treif d'Oraita, right outside of it you're not concerned.
So now the גמרא Gemara says, okay,
רבא אמר מאי לא חשו להם חכמים משום בישולי עובדי כוכבים? Rava
amar mai lo chashu lahem Chachamim mishum bishulei ovdei kochavim? No, רבא
Rava says if there was a concern, you know the analogy is
not to an איסור דאורייתא. issur d'Oraita. The analogy is to an
איסור דרבנן. issur d'Rabbanan. We're not concerned that the non-Jew
maybe you know cooked for you and that would make it אסור
assur because of בישול עכו"ם. bishul akum. בישול עכו"ם, Bishul akum, like
you know maybe he lit the fire for you, he stirred the
pot for you, we're not concerned about that איסור דרבנן. issur d'Rabbanan.
והכא נמי לא חשו להם חכמים משום יום אידם. V'hacha nami lo
chashu lahem Chachamim mishum Yom Edam. And here too they were not
concerned of יום אידם. Yom Edam. So we're only dealing with a
דרבנן, d'Rabbanan, and this by the way makes it clear that we're
not dealing with necessarily at least for רבא Rava like some special
scenario of a market day, we're just dealing with the generic issue
of a יום איד. Yom Eid. Even though there's a יום איד
Yom Eid going on in עזה, Azah, we're not concerned with the
יום איד Yom Eid outside of עזה. Azah. Okay, so that's more
aligned with the types of things we were talking about.
And then you know רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot discuss, well what
does this mean? Like why you know there's also איסור issur or
like does רבא Rava feel in general we are concerned that people
might be handling you know money of עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? Or
does you know how does he feel about the meat case and
about the נבילה neveilah case? Are those things that he generally is
concerned about, isn't concerned about? But we're going to bracket that. רבא
Rava is saying the point of the analogy was not to talk
about money of עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, maybe that's never a concern.
Okay, certainly on a יום איד Yom Eid that's never a concern.
And the really point of it was to talk about a concern
of a דרבנן. d'Rabbanan. That we're not, that we don't have a
concern of a דרבנן. d'Rabbanan. Okay,
רבה בר עולא אמר לא חשו להם חכמים משום צינורא. Rabbah bar
Ulla amar lo chashu lahem Chachamim mishum tzinora. No, that we're not
concerned about something even one degree removed. Not even direct בישול עכו"ם
bishul akum concern, but a splatter. A splatter will go out from
the pot of the non-Jew and hit the pot of the Jew.
Now that would sound like it could be an איסור דאורייתא issur
d'Oraita because the spot of the pot of the non-Jew is נבילה.
neveilah. But you know תוספות Tosafot says no, it would be a
scenario where it would be בטל. batel. So you know they wouldn't
be concerned about it because it would be first of all it
wouldn't you know it would be just a splatter, it would be
like removed from it, not the thing itself and who knows that
it would happen, and even if it would happen it wouldn't you
know it would be בטל. batel. So they weren't concerned about that.
והכא נמי לא חשו להם חכמים משום לפני אידיהן. V'hacha nami lo
chashu lahem Chachamim mishum lifnei edeihen. So the analogy is it's sort
of like an extension of the thing, not the thing itself. So
he's saying outside we would not be concerned with the days preceding
the holiday. But it sounds like on the holiday
itself עזה Azah would actually you know be, I mean the אטלוזא
Atloza would actually be close enough to עזה Azah that on the
יום איד Yom Eid itself it would be a problem. But at
least when you're a little bit more removed like the spray, at
least you're you know the days before יום איד Yom Eid then
that place is not a concern. Okay. מהו לילך לשם? Mahu leileich
l'sham? Now going on to the next part of the משנה. Mishna.
What is the story about going there? תנו רבנן עיר שיש בה
עבודת כוכבים אסור ליכנס לתוכה. Tano Rabbanan ir she'yesh bah avodat kochavim
assur likaneis l'tochah.
If a city has in it עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, and again
we're going to say it means that it's a יום איד Yom
Eid of עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, either a market day or a
יום איד, Yom Eid, but anyway there's a lot of celebration going
on in the city, then you cannot enter into it because Guys,
again, it looks like you're going to participate, or it looks like
the going itself is a form of participation. ולא מתוכה לעיר אחרת,
v'lo mitochah l'ir acheret, דברי רבי מאיר, divrei Rabbi Meir, and you
can't go from it to another city, these are the words of
Rabbi Meir. Now that doesn't really make any sense. If you live
in the city, you're not allowed to leave the city when they're
having their celebrations? It sounds like what Rabbi Meir is saying is
you're not allowed to go into it even if you are going
to proceed and leave it and continue on to another city. Okay,
it doesn't matter that you're just cutting through, you're not allowed to
go into it. וחכמים אומרים, v'Chachamim omrim, and the Sages say, and
this is the opinion in our משנה, Mishna, כל זמן שהדרך מיוחדת
לאותו מקום אסור, kol zman shehaderech miyuchedet l'oto makom assur, אינה דרך
מיוחדת לאותו מקום מותר. einah derech miyuchedet l'oto makom mutar. If the
path terminates in the city, then you can't go. It's looking like
you're participating or going to participate. If however the path continues on,
then you can go and even go and stop there, because anybody
seeing you going will assume you're continuing on. So Rabbi Meir doesn't
permit it even if you in fact continue on, and the חכמים
Chachamim permit it even if you stop as long as the road
continues on. Okay, so that's a question about appearances and looking like
you're participating or going to participate. It's like essentially a מראית עין
marit ayin concern. And now we're going to deal with other forms
of מראית עין. marit ayin. ישב לו קוץ בפני עבודה זרה. yashav
lo kotz bifnei avodah zarah.
Let's say you got a thorn in your foot right in front
of an idol. So לא ישחה ויטלנו, lo yishcheh v'yitlenu,
do not bend down in order to pull out your thorn because
it looks like you're bowing down in front of the idol, מפני
שנראה כמשתחוה לעבודה זרה, mipnei shenireh k'mishtachaveh l'avodah zarah,
it looks like you're bowing down to the idol. ואם אינו נראה
מותר, v'im eino nireh mutar, but if
it does not appear that way, it is permissible. The גמרא Gemara
will discuss that phrase in a minute. נתפזרו לו מעותיו בפני עבודה
זרה, nitpazru lo maotav bifnei avodah zarah,
if your wallet, your money purse breaks open and your money scatters
in front of the idol, לא ישחה וילקטם, lo yishcheh v'yilketem,
you should not bend down and pick them up, מפני שנראה כמשתחוה
לעבודה זרה, mipnei shenireh k'mishtachaveh l'avodah zarah, it looks like you're bowing
down. Now you can sort of kick some money or do other
things to sort of get the money, but do not bend down
because in a way that somebody at a distance, it will look
like you're bowing to the idol. ואם אינו נראה מותר, v'im eino
nireh mutar,
but if it does not appear that way, it's permissible. מעיין המושך
לפני עבודה זרה, ma'ayan hamoshech lifnei avodah zarah, if you have a
well, a spring of water that is coming out like in front
of, and sometimes they would have this, they'd make these pools and
water flowing and there'd be a statue of an idol over it,
לפני עבודה זרה, lifnei avodah zarah, לא ישחה וישתה, lo yishcheh v'yishteh,
do not bend down to drink from the water, מפני שנראה כמשתחוה
לעבודה זרה, mipnei shenireh k'mishtachaveh l'avodah zarah, it looks like you're bowing
down to the idol. ואם אינו נראה מותר, v'im eino nireh mutar,
but if it does not appear that way, it is permissible. פרצופות
המקלחים מים לכרכים, partzufot hamakallchim mayim likrachim,
similarly if you have like a face of a god and they,
you can see this in some cities in Europe, where they have
like again, a spring or water flowing out of an open mouth,
it makes a statue or like a bust of a god and
then the water flows out of the open mouth. So לכרכים, likrachim,
and then from that the water is flowing to the cities, לא
יניח פיו על פיהם וישתה, lo yaniche piv al pihem v'yishteh, do
not put your mouth against the mouth of this face
and drink, מפני שנראה כמנשק לעבודה זרה, mipnei shenireh k'menashek l'avodah zarah,
it looks like you're kissing the idol. Even though that doesn't look
like you're bowing down, it's still an איסור דאורייתא, issur d'Oraita, although
it's not עבודה, avodah, but to hug, to kiss, to show acts
of honoring the idol even if it's not an act of worship
would also be forbidden and that's the way it will appear. כיוצא
בו, kayotzei bo, similarly on a,
from a completely different perspective, but talking about things about drinking that
are problematic, לא יניח פיו על סילון וישתה, lo yaniche piv al
silon v'yishteh, do not put your mouth on a pipe and drink,
מפני הסכנה, mipnei hasakanah, because of the danger. Okay, מאי אינו נראה?
mai eino nireh? Now that's the end of the ברייתא. braita. Now,
what does this mean that if it does not appear it is
not a problem? אילימא דלא מיתחזי, ileima d'lo mitchazi,
you're not visible, you're doing it but nobody is around, nobody is
seeing you? ואמר רב יהודה אמר רב כל מקום שאסרו חכמים מפני
מראית עין אפילו בחדרי חדרים אסור. v'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav kol
makom she'asru Chachamim mipnei marit ayin afilu b'chadrei chadarim assur. Wherever the
Sages said that something was forbidden because מראית עין, marit ayin, even
if you're in your innermost chambers it is forbidden. So it doesn't
matter if nobody is there, it's still forbidden because of מראית עין.
marit ayin. Now I should say something about this because there's two
ways of explaining this. One is you think nobody is seeing you
but you never know, somebody might be seeing you. The other way
of explaining this is that
part of the problem with מראית עין marit ayin is not just
that people will see you and they'll suspect you and so on,
but it's that for yourself you're breaking a taboo, you're doing something
that feels wrong, that looks like it's wrong, and that's a problem
even if nobody else is around, just in terms of the way
it breaks a taboo. for yourself. So anyway, it doesn't matter if
nobody is seeing you, it is still forbidden. So the גמרא Gemara
says,
by the way, I should also say מכל מקום שאסרו חכמים מפני
מראית עין. mikol makom she-asru chachamim mipnei maris ayin. There's a general
assumption in the פוסקים poskim that anything that looks like you're doing
an איסור issur is automatically אסור assur because of מראית עין, maris
ayin, but there is an opinion in the פוסקים poskim that no,
there are certain things that the חז"ל chazal forbade because of מראית
עין, maris ayin, but we don't say that across the board there's
a generic מראית עין maris ayin that always applies, you know, it's
only things that they chose to make forbidden out of a concern
of מראית עין maris ayin that are forbidden. Again, that's not the
general approach, but it is an approach of some פוסקים. poskim. Anyway,
so אינו נראה eino nireh cannot mean that nobody is seeing you
because that would not make a difference. אלא אימא, ela eima, so
what does it mean? אם אינו נראה כמשתחווה לעבודת כוכבים מותר. im
eino nireh k'mishtachaveh l'avodas kochavim mutar. That if by context it does
not seem to people, it'll be obvious, you know, not necessarily obvious
that people will obviously recognize that there's something else could be going
on here. It's a very normal thing. You know, people will see
you picking up the money or it'll be by the way you're
doing it doesn't look like you're bowing down, you're hopping around and
on one foot trying to pull the thorn out. Nobody, even though
you're bending a little, nobody is going to think that that's a
bowing down. And that's by מראית עין, maris ayin, it doesn't have
to be that it's totally obvious what you're doing. It just has
to be that the permissible interpretation is a reasonable one. Like the
case of the משנה. Mishnah. If the road continues beyond the city,
then people, you know, can reasonably assume that you're going beyond the
city.
So that suffices. You know, it's always the question about like going
into the McDonalds to use the bathroom, right? So if that's what
how much does it have to be clear to everyone that's what's
happening? No. To get out of מראית עין maris ayin it has
to be that that's the, you know, a reasonable person will understand,
oh yeah, he's probably just going in to use the bathroom, that's
enough. Okay, so that's what it means. If it doesn't if it
doesn't appear that way that you're doing an איסור, issur, if it's
a reasonable interpretation is otherwise, then it is permissible.
וצריכה, u'tzricha, and we had to tell you that all three cases
here are forbidden. Why not just tell me one case is forbidden
and I'll just generalize that don't do things that look like you're
bowing down to עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? וצריכה. u'tzricha. דאי תנא קוץ
משום דאפשר למיזל קמיה ומשקליה, d'ee tana kotz mishum d'efshar l'meizil kamei
u'mishklei,
if it had the case of the thorn and I would have
said, okay, by the thorn we don't let you do it because
you can just, you know, walk a few steps away and take
it out, so there's no urgency to do it, so we say
don't do it. אבל מעות דלא אפשר, aval ma'os d'lo efshar, but
money, you can't go somewhere else, your money is here. So we
might think that we allow you to pick up your money. We're
not concerned about מראית עין maris ayin if it means you're going
to have to lose your money.
אימא לא, eima lo, so I might think no. So it told
no, even there it's a concern of מראית עין maris ayin and
either figure out how to do it that it doesn't look like
you're bowing down or don't bow down and kick or something like
that, or lose the money. ואי תנא מעות דממונא, v'ee tana ma'os
d'mamona, if it just said you know, the money you have to
abandon if you have no choice, fine,
that I get. אבל קוץ דאיכא צערא, aval kotz d'ika tza'ara, but
I might think that when I have a thorn in my foot,
the pain, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe that you would let me
do and wouldn't we worry about מראית עין. maris ayin. So it
had to tell you both the case of the thorn and the
case of the money to tell you even though there's pain and
even though there's no other options, you have to go ahead and
forgo it rather than looking like you're, and the מראית עין maris
ayin concern is such that you have to accept those losses. ואי
תנא הני תרתי, v'ee tana hani tarti, and if it had just
said those two, משום דליכא סכנה, mishum d'leika sakana, that's because there's
no danger. אבל מעיין דאיכא סכנה, aval ma'ayan d'ika sakana, but
when it comes to a spring that there could be a danger
if you don't drink, דאילו לא שתי מיית, d'ilu lo shasi mayis,
if you don't drink you could die. אימא לא, eima lo, I
might think that you know, that then you would be allowed to
drink from it. צריכה, tzricha, it had to tell me that case
as well about drinking, about bending down and drinking. Let's just finish
this because I want to go back to that סכנה sakana point,
but let's just turn onto the י"ב ע"ב. yud bais amud bais.
פרצופות למה לי, partzofos lama li, and now why did it give
the case about the water coming out of the faces? Now one
reason it could have given that case, תוספות Tosafos points out, is
because it doesn't look like you're bowing down, it looks like you're
kissing, which is less of an איסור. issur. But okay, either way,
presumably once you're concerned with one, you'd be concerned with the other.
So why do you have to tell me that that's אסור assur
as well? משום דקבעי למתני כיוצא בו לא יניח פיו על גבי
הסילון וישתה מפני הסכנה. mishum d'ka'ba'ee l'misni k'yotzei bo lo yanich piv
al gabei ha'silon v'yishteh mipnei ha'sakana. Okay,
because it wanted to get to the other point about drinking from
directly, say you don't put your mouth on this you know, idol,
you don't put your mouth directly on a pipe because of danger.
So we wanted to make the transition to talk about that, so
that's why we gave this case of the פרצופות. partzofos. Now, I
should say something about the case of the what do you call
it, of the סכנה. sakana. You know, a simple reading of this
גמרא Gemara says that מראית עין maras ayin of עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah is so חמור chamur that it would you would have to
die rather than do it. You know, that's what's said, even because
of סכנה. sakana. And there could be a logic for it. You
know, the question is the same way עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah itself
is יהרג ואל יעבור, yehareg v'al ya'avor, so there's always like an
interesting למדות lamdus question that things that are sort of איסורים issurim
that are derivative and connected to another איסור issur are do they
have the same weight? So for example, is לפני עיוור lifnei iver
of a certain עבירה, aveira, if I am causing you to be
נכשל nichshal in חילול שבת chilul Shabbos God forbid or יין לנזיר,
yayin l'nazir, is that just a generic איסור issur of לפני עיוור?
lifnei iver?
Or is there a is it like a like a
like an extension of the איסור, issur, you know, takes on some
of the weight of the איסור issur of the thing that I'm
מכשיל machshil you in. So in that way like a לפני עיוור
lifnei iver of חילול שבת chilul Shabbos I would have done more
of an עבירה aveira than a לפני עיוור lifnei iver of an
איסור נזיר issur nazir because one was a חיוב כרת chiyuv kares
and the other like a, you know, and the other was a
what do you call it was was a simple לאו. lav. Or
חצי שיעור. chatzi shiur. Is חצי שיעור chatzi shiur of חמץ chametz
on פסח Pesach more חמור chamur than חצי שיעור chatzi shiur of
נבלה? neveila? One is a כרת, kares, חמץ chametz on פסח Pesach
is כרת, kares, נבלה neveila is a simple לאו. lav. How about
חצי שיעור? chatzi shiur? Is that just a generic איסור? issur? Or
does that somehow derivative of of the individual איסור issur it's connected
to? So with that question about מראית עין, maras ayin, you could
say is מראית עין maras ayin of עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, is
it like עבודה זרה? Avodah Zarah? And therefore יהרג ואל יעבור. yehareg
v'al ya'avor. So that is a possible read of this גמרא, Gemara,
but that is quite extreme. And most פוסקים poskim do not read
it that way. ראשונים Rishonim and פוסקים poskim they say when the
גמרא Gemara says you could die, the גמרא Gemara is just exaggerating.
You know what it means, you know, when you're dealing with water,
water is something that's a source of life etc. I might think
that having people giving, you know, allowing people to drink when they're
thirsty is a more urgent issue and I would have allowed it,
but of course you would not have to give up your life
rather than מראית עין maras ayin for עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. And
actually, you know, this issue comes up in the פוסקים poskim about
a whole case where people had to bow down when you know
the priest was walking in the Middle
Ages and פוסקים poskim had to deal with like how to manage
those situations when they were expected to bow down and you know
and it would be a real concern of possible you know not
only looking like being עובד oveid but you know maybe that's what
was being asked of them. So the רמ"א Rema here deals with
this in יורה דעה ק"נ סעיף ג' Yoreh De'ah kuf nun se'if
gimmel and on this פסק psak about exactly our case and the
פסק psak in שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch is פרצופות מקלחים מים לפני
אלילים לא יניח פיו על פיהם וישתה מפני שנראה כמנשק לאלילים. partzufot
mekalchin mayim lifnei elilim lo yaniach piv al pihem v'yishteh mipnei she-nir'eh
k'menashek l'elilim. Okay, fine. He does not mention סכנה. sakana. Here's what
the רמ"א Rema says: יש אומרים דכל שאינו אסור אלא מפני מראית
עין כגון בענין זה אם יש סכנה בדבר כגון אם ימות אם
לא ישתה מותר לשתות ואין בזה משום יהרג ואל יעבור. Yesh omrim
de-kol she-eino assur ela mipnei maras ayin k'gon b'inyan zeh, im yesh
sakana b'davar k'gon im yamut im lo yishteh mutar lishtos v'ein be-zeh
mishum yehareg v'al ya'avor. So he says it in the name of
יש אומרים Yesh Omrim which is the ר"ן, Ran, but that clearly
is the פסק psak and I should also mention that that
he says the same about about לפני עיוור, lifnei iver, that לפני
עיוור lifnei iver of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah is not treated as
יהרג ואל יעבור yehareg v'al ya'avor like עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah is.
Okay, now I should mention that the גר"א Gra takes issue with
this and the גר"א Gra basically makes it sound like he wants
to rule like the פשט pshat of the גמרא Gemara that מראית
עין maras ayin of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah is יהרג ואל יעבור,
yehareg v'al ya'avor,
and he also references the classic מדרש midrash about המן Haman that
everybody had to bow down to המן Haman and המן Haman wore
an idol around his neck and so on and and that would
be a case of מרדכי Mordechai didn't bow down, shouldn't look like
he's bowing down to the idol, is that a would that be
a case of יהרג ואל יעבור, yehareg v'al ya'avor, you know and
that's why מרדכי Mordechai would refuse to do it. So really very
fascinating question and to some degree even though מראית עין maras ayin
tends to be, you know, rabbinic and seemed as, you know, much
less weighty than something like לפני עיוור lifnei iver you could understand
actually why מראית עין maras ayin of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah would
be יהרג ואל יעבור yehareg v'al ya'avor and לפני עיוור lifnei iver
would not, לפני עיוור lifnei iver is a simple לאו lav whereas
מראית עין maras ayin of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah part of the
idea of ואהבת את ה' אלהיך, v'ahavta es Hashem Elokecha, you know
that you have to give up your life rather than betray your
faith, maybe if it looks to people like you're betraying your faith
then it doesn't matter whether you actually are or not and maybe
effectively that becomes the יהרג ואל יעבור yehareg v'al ya'avor of עבודה
זרה. Avodah Zarah. So the גר"א Gra seems to give weight to
that read, although the רמ"א Rema seems to very much side with
the position that it is not יהרג ואל יעבור. yehareg v'al ya'avor.
And then he deals with the case we were discussing. And then
he says the following. He says שרים או כהנים שיש להם צורות
עבודות כוכבים בבגדיהם. sarim o kohanim she-yesh lahem tzurot avodot kochavim b'vigdeihem.
If you have, you know,
lords or priests that have, you know, images of עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah you know, maybe crosses, crucifixes on their garments, או שנושאים צורת
חמה לפניהם כדרך ההגמונים, o shenosim tzorat chama lifneihem kederech hahagmonim, or
they're, you know, carrying a picture of like a sun in front
of them, they're doing some type of a processional through the town
that they would do on a religious holiday. אסור להשתחוות להם
או להסיר כובע לפניהם.
רק בדרך שאינו נראה. Assur lehishtachavot lahem o lehasir kova lifneihem. Rak
bederech she'eino nireh. So he says, you know, you can't—it's expected that
you're supposed to bow down when they pass or take off your
hat. But the problem is is that then it will look like
you're bowing down to, you know, the idols, the images. So he
says, so אלא רק בדרך שאינו נראה, כמו שנתפזרו מעותיו או שיקלם
לפניהם קודם בואם, וכן יסיר הכובע וישתחוה קודם בואם. ella rak bederech
she'eino nireh, kimo shenitpazru me'otav o sheyikalm lifneihem kodem bo'am, vechein yasir
hakova veyishtachaveh kodem bo'am. So he says, you know, you do it
in a way that it doesn't look like you're bowing down to
them, like you drop your money and you bend down to pick
your money. So it's very funny. It's the גמרא Gemara's case was
you're bending down to pick your money, looks like you're bowing down.
Here you're expected to bow down because of you're showing honor to
them. But because this they're doing a procession for עבודה זרה avodah
zarah it looks like you're bowing down to the עבודה זרה. avodah
zarah. So the dropping of the money is the way in which
it makes it look like you're doing something other than that. Or
you know you happen to have your hat off before they pass
so it's not being done in the context of them passing. And
then it says, ויש מקילים בדבר, חוב ידוע שגם עובדי כוכבים אינם
מסירים כובע ומשתחוים לצורת החמה רק לשר, והטוב להחמיר כסברה ראשונה. veyesh
mekilim bedavar, hov yadu'a shegam ovdei kochavim einam mesirim kova umishtachavim letzurat
hachama rak lassar, vehatov lehachmir kassevara rishona. And then he says, and
this gets to the אינו נראה eino nireh that people understand that
when you're bowing down you're not bowing down, you know, to the
idol or to the image, you're bowing down as a show of
deference to the personage that is passing in front of you. So
there you have exactly a common case that would be this and
how do you deal with it that it's not מראית עין? maris
ayin? Does context make it clear enough? And maybe the dropping of
the money דווקא davka is the way that gets it out of
the מראית עין. maris ayin. But also very important bottom line question
about whether we פוסקין paskin that this is מראית עין maris ayin
in עבודה זרה avodah zarah is יהרג ואל יעבור. yehareg ve'al ya'avor.
Okay so now let's move on to this other point this really
completely digression point about drinking water direct from the pipes because of
danger. So the גמרא Gemara says top three lines from the top,
י"ב עמוד ב'. yod bet amud bet. מאי סכנה, Mai sakana, what
is the danger we're concerned about? עלוקה, Aluka, a leech. You'll swallow
a leech and then it'll get into your digestive system and that
will be a real danger. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, our rabbis taught,
לא ישתה אדם מים לא מן הנהרות ולא מן האגמים. lo yishte
adam mayim lo min haneharot velo min ha'agamim. You should not drink
water straight from the rivers or from the ponds. ולא בפיו ולא
בידו אחת, Velo befiv velo beyado achat, not directly, not directly putting
your mouth down and drinking and not using one hand and sort
of shoveling the water, scooping the water into your mouth. Because then
you're not like having an opportunity to look at the water that
you're holding on to and to see whether there's any insects or
you know or like a water creatures or leeches in them.
So reaches, I'm sorry, I said leak, I meant leeches. Leak would
be funny to be in the water but that would not be
a danger. All right let's read that again. מאי סכנה, Mai sakana,
what is the danger? עלוקה, Aluka, a leech. Leech. תנו רבנן Tanu
rabanan לא ישתה אדם מים לא מן הנהרות ולא מן האגמים ולא
בפיו ולא בידו אחת. lo yishte adam mayim lo min haneharot velo
min ha'agamim velo befiv velo beyado achat. Don't drink it straight from
the pond or the river with directly with your mouth or with
one hand because you won't be able to be looking if there
are leeches. ואם שתה דמו בראשו. Ve'im shata damo berosho. And if
you did drink it that way then your blood is on your
head. Then you know you are if—if—if you know
get
injured as a result, you know if you swallow a leech and
you die as a result it's your own fault you've brought it
upon yourself.
Okay בפני הסכנה bifnei hasakana because you it is dangerous to do
this. מאי סכנה? Mai sakana? What is the סכנה? sakana? So the
גמרא Gemara again says סכנת עלוקה sakanas aluka is the fear of
leeches. מסייע ליה לרבי חנינא. Mesaye'a lei lerabi chanina. This supports Rabbi
Chanina. דאמר רבי חנינא הבולע נימא של מים מותר להחם לו חמים
בשבת. De'amar rabi chanina habole'a nima shel mayim mutar lehacham lo chamim
beshabbat.
If one swallowed a water leech, you know then you can heat
up water on שבת Shabbat because apparently the understanding was that A:
it was a סכנה sakana as we've been saying and the way
to deal with it is that if you drink hot water that
that hot water might do something to kill or to neutralize the
leech that is now in your digestive system. Okay. ומעשה
באחד שבלע נימא של מים. Uma'aseh be'echad shebala nima shel mayim. And
there was a story that a person swallowed a water leech. ואתא
רבי נחמיה, Ve'ata rabi nechemya, and Rabbi Nechemya came, or some have
רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina which would be the same Rabbi Chanina we
just mentioned. החם לו חמים בשבת. Hechem lo chamim beshabbat. To heat
up water exactly according to his ruling. Now אדדהכי והכי, ad dehacki
vehacki, while you're waiting for the water to heat up, you know
what can you do? Is there anything immediate that you can do?
So אדדהכי והכי, ad dehacki vehacki, what do you do? אמר רב
הונא בריה דרב יהושע Amar rav huna breih derav yehoshua
ליגמע חלא, ligma chala, swallow vinegar. Maybe also that will like kill
or neutralize the leech enough till you can drink the hot water
which will really do the job. אמר רב אידי בר אבין האי
מאן דבלע זיבורא מחייא. Amar rav idi bar abin hai man debala
zibura michaya. If somebody goes swallows a live wasp,
excuse me, I misread that, האי מאן דבלע זיבורא, hai man devala
zibura, if somebody swallows a wasp, מחייא לא חיי. michya lo chaye.
If somebody swallows a wasp, מחייא לא חיי, michya lo chaye, he
will not live. מיהו, mihu, לשיקייה רביעיתא דחלא, lishkiyei revi'isa de'chala, some
gauze, but what he should do is at least drink a רביעיתא
דחלא, revi'isa de'chala, which is like three ounces of like of pungent
vinegar. מחייא, michya, אפשר דחיי פורתא עד דמיפקד אביתיה. efshar de'chaye purta
ad demifkad aveite. It's possible that that will keep him alive long
enough that he can set his affairs to order. Okay, so not
only are water leeches a סכנה sakana and actually there's a way
of dealing with them, you know, vinegar will neutralize it for a
while and hot water will deal with it completely, but apparently swallowing
a wasp is will definitely kill you, again I assume it's a
live wasp,
and but there's ways that you can give yourself a little more
time.
תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, לא ישתה אדם מים בלילה, lo yishte adam
mayim ba'layla, you should not drink water at night. And here we're
no longer dealing with a concern about leeches or wasps but about
שדים. shedim. All right. So and and so ואם שתה דמו בראשו,
ve'im shata damo be'rosho, and if you drank then your blood is
on your own head, any danger you're exposing yourself to danger and
you are to blame מפני הסכנה mipnei ha'sakana because of the danger.
מאי סכנה, mai sakana, what's the סכנה? sakana? סכנת שברירי, sakanas shavrizi,
it is the סכנה sakana of שברירי shavrizi which is a type
of a רש"י Rashi says שד הממונה על מכת סנורים, shed ha'memuneh
al makas sanverim, it is the שד shed that affects blindness and
again, you know, שדים shedim are out at night, so you are
exposing yourself to the danger of the שדים shedim and to danger
of blindness. ואם צחי מאי תקנתיה, ve'im tzachi mai takante, but if
you're thirsty at night what should you do? אי איכא אחרינא בהדיה,
ei ika achrina bahadei, so if there's somebody else with you in
the room,
ליתעריה, litariei, then you should wake him up because again שדים shedim
do not, you know, get people when they're alone.
ולימא ליה ve'leima leh and you should say to him, צחינא מיא,
tzachina maya, I'm thirsty for water so you sort of involve another
person, you know, in the process and then that scares away the
שדים. shedim. צחינא מיא. tzachina maya. ואם לאו, ve'im lav, but if
another person is not around,
then
נקרקש בקנתמא דחצבא, nekarkesh be'kantamah de'chatzva, you should go ahead and like
bang on the lid of a jug ונימא לאנפשיה ve'neima le'nafshei and
you should say to yourself, פלוני בר פלונית, ploni bar plonis, so
and so, the son of so and so meaning your own name,
שמעון בן ראובן Shimon ben Reuven if that's the guy's name,
אמרה לך אימך, amra lach imach, your mother said to you, איזדהר
משברירי ברירי רירי ירי רי, izdahir mi'shavrizi brizi rizi yizi rizi, be
careful of the שברירי ברירי רירי ירי רי shavrizi brizi rizi yizi
rizi and then you sort of say the name cutting off B-I-N-G-O
cutting down one letter each time and that somehow is some type
of an
incantation, a לחש lachash that will counteract this demon of שברירי shavrizi
בכסי חיורי be'chasi chivri in white that is found in white cups.
Okay and that will be an incantation that will neutralize the this
this שד. shed. All right, we will end with that.